A Guide to the Dayton M. Kohler Papers, 1889-1972
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Dayton M. Kohler Papers, 1889-1971
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms1971-002
4.5 cu. ft. 9 boxes
Papers of Dayton M. Kohler, professor of English at Virginia Tech and an authority on modern American literature. Includes correspondence from noted authors, typescript drafts of essay-reviews for Masterplots, manuscripts of articles written by Kohler, and a collection of materials associated with various authors.
Kohler, Dayton M., 1907-1972
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The Dayton M. Kohler Papers were donated to Special Collections in several separate accruals in 1971 and 1972.
Biographical Note
Dayton McCue Kohler, son of Edwin and Bertha Kohler, was born in Pennsylvania on September 24, 1906. The 1910 and 1920 censuses list the family living in Wormleysburg (Cumberland County), Pennsylvania. The younger Kohler graduated from Gettysburg College with a bachelor's degree in 1928 and obtained his master's degree at the University of Virginia in 1929. That same year, Kohler was hired by Virginia Tech as an instructor of English. By 1932, Kohler had been promoted to assistant professor. The 1946 university academic catalog lists him as an associate professor beginning in 1946, and professor in 1957. Kohler married Jean Stewart Ogden in 1937. Kohler retired in 1970 and was named professor emeritus of English. At the time of his death, on February 1, 1972, he was a resident of Fredericksburg, Virginia.
Scope and Content Note
This collections contains the papers of Dayton M. Kohler, a professor of English at Virginia Tech (1929-1970) and an authority on modern American literature. The collection contains correspondence, drafts and galley proofs of literary essay-reviews for publications edited by Kohler, manuscript drafts for articles written by Kohler, and a collection of materials relating to various authors. Among the noted authors most prominently featured in the collection are Willa Cather, Conrad Richter, Carl Sandburg, James Still, and Jesse Stuart. Within the correspondence are single letters from a number of other noted authors, including Sherwood Anderson, F. Scott Fitzgerald, and Katherine Anne Porter.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in six series:
Series I. Correspondence, 1927-1972. This series contains letters to Kohler, the overwhelming majority being from various authors. Much of the correspondence is routine in nature, relating to literary essay-reviews. Among the letters, however, are a number from noted authors, including Sherwood Anderson, Willa Cather, F. Scott Fitzgerald, Earl Hamner Jr., MacKinlay Kantor, Archibald MacLeish, Joyce Carol Oates, Katherine Anne Porter, Reynolds Price, Conrad Richter, Carl Sandburg (and his daughter, Helga Sandburg Golby), James Still, and Eudora Welty. (Still and Stuart seem to have been among Kohler's more frequent correspondents, each represented by substantial letters.) While many of the letters in this series are brief and businesslike, a few are more personal in nature. The letter from Porter, for example, offers a lengthy assessment of critical reviews of her Ship of Fools. Likewise, a pair of letters by Mildred Bennett, an authority on Willa Cather, provide personal insights on Cather and her family. Among the other correspondents in the series are artists Archer Lawrie and Dale Nichols. The series is arranged by correspondent name. Series II. Essays, [1931]-1952. This brief series contains a selection Kohler's manuscript drafts of articles on various literary subjects. Many of the drafts include notes on where and when the piece was eventually published. Included in the series is a draft of Kohler's introduction to the 1965 Harper & Row edition of Lord Jim. Arranged chronologically.
Series III, Essay-Review Drafts, 1967-1971. Included in this series are drafts (mostly typescripts) of essay-reviews submitted by various reviewers for literary publications edited by Kohler, mostly for the series Masterplots. The drafts include manuscript revisions. Arranged by title and date of publication, then alphabetically by title of work reviewed. (The essays for the 1968-1970 editions of Masterplots had been split by Kohler into two separate sets per year, each arranged alphabetically within the set. The order in which Kohler separated and arranged the sets has been maintained.)
Series IV. Galley Proofs, 1966-[1969]. This series contains galley proofs received from the publisher for two editions of Masterplots. The proofs include manuscript revisions. Arranged by publication title.
Series V. Authors, 1889-1967. Found in this series is a collection of materials relating to various authors. The series includes such items as ephemera, printed material, autographs, and photographs. Many authors are represented by nothing more than notices that accompanied books sent to Kohler as review copies. Among the more significant items in the series, however, are such materials as an advance preview of Donald Barthelme's Come Back, Doctor Caligari, radio-play scripts for "Moses" by Walter D. Edmonds and "Rifles for Washington" by Elsie Singmaster, printed and other publicity materials relating to Robert Frost, an envelope purportedly addressed by Nathaniel Hawthorne, a letter written by Oliver Wendell Holmes, photographs of Kohler with James Still at Morehead University Library, autographs of Archibald MacLeish and Thomas Nast, and printed material and autographed notes from Carl Sandburg. The largest set of materials in the series relates to Jesse Stuart and includes several pieces of printed material, many including personal notes from Stuart to Kohler. Also included is a photograph of Stuart by photographer Earl Palmer. The series is arranged alphabetically by name.
Series VI. Books and Publishing, 1955-1971. The materials in this small series relate to Kohler's general interest in literature and consist largely of printed materials. Included is a copy of Kohler's own booklet, Books and Reading and several issues of The Hollins Critic, published by Hollins University. The series also contains working lists of books reviewed in some editions of Masterplots. Arranged by tiem type.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Materials
A keyword search on Kohler's name in the library's catalog will provide the titles of works the library purchased from Kohler's collection in 1971.
Separated Materials
The following books were removed from the collection and cataloged for the Rare Book Collection:
Strong, L. A. G. A Letter to W. B. Yeats. Hogarth Letters 6. London: Leonard & Virginia Woolf, 1932.
Woodbridge, Hensley C. Jesse Stuart: a Bibliography. Harrogate, TN: Lincoln Memorial University Press.
Woodbridge, Hensley C. Jesse Stuart: a Bibliography for May, 1960 - May, 1965. Rpt. from The Register of the Kentucky Historical Society 63.4 (October 1965).
Index Terms
Subjects:
Virginia Agricultural and Mechanical College and Polytechnic Institute; Virginia Polytechnic Institute; Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Local Subjects:
Faculty; University Archives
Contents List
- Series I. Correspondence, 1927-1972
  - A-B (Box-folder 1-1)
    - Allen, Gay Wilson, 1957
    - Allen, Walter, 1957
    - Anderson, Sherwood, [ca. 1928]
    - Apple, Max, 1970
    - Arnow, Harriette, 1961
    - Atchison, Ray M., 1967
    - Auld, Louis, 1966
    - Barney, Stephen, 1965
    - Batson, Eric J., 1957-1958
    - Baumbach, Jonathan, 1964
    - Beard, James F. Jr., 1956-1957
    - Bender, Todd K., 1965
    - Bennett, Mildred R., 1951
    - Bentley, Eric, 1957
    - Berman, Ron, 1966-1969
    - Betts, Doris, [1971], n.d.
    - Bingham, Mary, 1966
    - Binkley, William O., 1962
    - Blotner, Joseph L., 1958-1962
    - Booth, Philip, 1962
    - Borck, Jim Springer, 1970
    - Bowen, Elizabeth, 1956
    - Bowling, Lawrence E., 1962-1971
    - Brand, John M., 1970, n.d.
    - Bravo Villarroel, Roberto, 1957-1965
    - Bruccoli, Matthew J., 1957 1957
  - C-E (Box-folder 1-2)
    - Cadle, Dean, 1960-1961
    - Cameron, Kenneth W., 1957
    - Cannaday, Robert W. Jr. 1957
    - Cather, Willa, 1939
    - Cecil, Lord David 1956
    - Champion, Larry S. 1966
    - Chase, Richard, 1956-1958
    - Clifford, James L. 1956
    - Cochran, Perry, 1964
    - Corrington, John William, 1970
    - Darrow, Diane M., 1966
    - Davis, H. C., 1936
    - Deal, N. Harvey, 1963
    - Derleth, August, 1959
    - Deutsch, Babette, 1955
    - Dillard, Richard, 1966, n.d.
    - DiStasi, Lawrence W., 1970
    - Duerksen, Roland A., n.d.
    - Dunn, Charles W., 1956
    - Dupee, Frederick W., 1956-1957
    - Eaton, Evelyn, 1957
    - Edmonds, Walter D., 1937
    - Ellis-Fermor, Una, 1956
    - Eyster, Warren, 1970
  - F-G (Box-folder 1-3)
    - Field, Bradford S. Jr., 1962
    - Fitzgerald, F. Scott, 1932
    - Francis, Robert, 1962
    - Garrett, George, 1964-1968
    - Gehle, Quentin, 1970
    - Geismer, Maxwell, 1970-1972
    - Gibson, Frank K. Jr., 1963
    - Goldby, Helga Sandburg, 1959
    - Grebstein, Sheldon, 1965
    - Green, James L., 1970
    - Green, Julian, 1940
    - Gregson, David E., 1971
    - Gries, Judy, 1965
    - Gwynn, Frederick L., 1957
  - H (Box-folder 1-4)
    - Hadas, Moses, 1956
    - Halperin, Irving, 1970
    - Hamilton, Edith, 1956
    - Hamner, Earl Jr., 1970
    - Hart, Dabney, 1964-1965
    - Hartley, Lodwick, 1957
    - Haskin, W., n.d.
    - Hazel, Robert, 1961-1970
    - Heffernan, James A., 1965
    - Henley, Elton F., 1962
    - Herlihy, James Leo, 1967
    - Hester, Erwin, 1965
    - Hogue, L. Lynn, 1971
  - I-K (Box-folder 1-5)
    - Johnson, Richard A., 1966
    - Johnson, Thomas H., 1957
    - Jones, Willis K., 1971
    - Kahn, Sy M., 1970
    - Kantor, MacKinlay, 1938
    - Karchmer, S. N., 1965
    - Keller, Abraham C., 1956-1957
    - Kent, [Carl?], 1940
    - Kent, Rockwell, 1943
    - Kermode, Frank, 1956-1958
    - Kieffer, John S., 1957
    - Kincheloe, Henderson, 1971
    - Knowles, Sidney, 1966
  - L (Box-folder 1-6)
    - Landon, Luann, 1965
    - Lasseter, Rollin A., 1971
    - Lavrin, Janko, 1956-1958
    - Lawrie, Archer, 1970
    - Lee, C. P., 1970
    - Lewars, Elsie Singmaster, 1939
    - Lindberg, Gary H., 1968
    - Lindley, Hilda L., 1970
    - Livesay, Dorothy, 1965
    - Locklin, Gerry, 1970, n.d.
    - Lytle, Andrew, 1964
  - M (Box-folder 1-7)
    - Mackey, Howard, 1961-1964
    - MacLeish, Archibald, 1932-1939
    - Macklin, F. Anthony, 1965
    - Madden, David, 1964-1969
    - Madden, Roberta, 1965-1971
    - Matson, Elizabeth, 1965
    - Matthews, Jack, 1968-1970
    - Matthieson, Peter, 1962
    - Mazzaro, Jerome, 1970
    - Mayhall, Jane, 1966
    - Meacham, Harry M., 1969
    - Minton, M. Cronan, 1971
    - Mitchell, Edward, 1968
    - Moore, Don, 1959-1970
    - Mueller, Lavonne, 1970
    - Muir, Kenneth, 1956
    - Murphy, Robert, n.d.
    - Myers, Margaret, 1971
  - N-Q (Box-folder 1-8)
    - Nichols, Dale, 1943
    - Nosworthy, J. M., 1956-1958
    - Oates, Joyce Carol, 1966
    - Owen, Guy, 1968, n.d.
    - Pinsker, Sanford, 1970
    - Plumly, Stanley, 1970-1971
    - Porter, Katherine Anne, 1966
    - Price, Reynolds, 1968
    - Prokosch, Frederic, n.d.
  - R (Box-folder 1-9)
    - Ratchford, Fannie, 1958
    - Rawlings, Marjorie Kinnan, 1944
    - Richardson, H. E. 1969-1971
    - Richter, Conrad, 1947-1967, n.d.
    - Roberts, Kenneth, n.d.
    - Robinson, W. R., 1966
    - Roby, Norman S., 1971
    - Rodenbeck, John, 1969
    - Rothschild, Herbert B. Jr., 1970
    - Rovit, Earl, 1965-1968, n.d.
    - Rueckert, Carla, 1963
  - Sa-Ss (Box-folder 1-10)
    - Salisbury, Ralph J., 1970
    - Sandburg, Carl 1951-1953
    - Schulman, Grace, 1970
    - See, Carolyn, 1966-1971
    - Shannon, Edgar F. Jr., 1957
    - Simpson, Lewis P., 1971
    - Slonim, Marc, 1956-1957
    - Smith, Marcus, 1970
    - Spiller, Robert E., 1956
  - Sta-Stt (Box-folder 1-11)
    - Stein, Allen F., 1969-1971
    - Stetler, Charles, n.d.
    - Stewart, Albert F., 1961-1966
    - Stewart, Randall, 1956-1957
    - Still, James, 1941-1971, n.d.
    - Stocker, Arthur F., 1963
  - Stu-Stz, [2 folders] (Box-folder 1-12)
    - Stuart, Jesse, 1955-1970, n.d.
  - Su-Sz (Box-folder 1-13)
    - Sultan, Stanley, 1970
    - Summers, Hollis, 1968
    - Sutcliff, Priscilla, 1965
  - T-Z (Box-folder 1-14)
    - Taylor, Henry, 1967-1970
    - Taylor, Peter, 1965
    - Turnbull, Andrew, 1965
    - Tyre, Nedra, 1967
    - Vandersee, Chuck, 1965-1968
    - White, Robert B. Jr., 1970
    - Wagenknecht, Edward, 1956
    - Warfel, Harry R., 1957
    - Weber, Carl J., 1956-1958
    - Webster, Harvey Curtis, 1966
    - Welty, Eudora, 1963-1964
    - Wescott, Glenway, 1962
    - White, Robert B. Jr. 1971
    - Wilder, Thornton, 1948
    - Williams, William Carlos, n.d.
    - Wilson, James Southall, 1956
    - Wylie, Elinor, 1927
    - Wright, Charles David, 1970
    - Yarmolinsky, Avrahm, 1956
    - Zabel, Morton Dauwen, 1956-1957
- Series II. Essays, [1931]-1952
  - [1931]-1952 (Box-folder 1-15)
  - n.d., [2 folders] (Box-folder 1-16)
- Series III. Essay-Review Drafts, 1967-1971
  - Masterplots Annual, 1967 (Box-folder 2-1-6)
  - Masterplots Annual [set 1], 1968 (Box-folder 2-7-11)
  - Masterplots Annual [set 2], 1968 (Box-folder 2-12-14)
  - Masterplots Annual [set 1], 1969 (Box-folder 3-1-5)
  - Masterplots Annual [set 2], 1969 (Box-folder 3-6-8)
  - Masterplots Annual [set 1], 1970 (Box-folder 3-9-13)
  - Masterplots Annual [set 2], 1970 (Box-folder 4-1-4)
  - Masterplots Annual, 1971 (Box-folder 4-5-5-2)
  - Masterpieces of World Literature in Digest Form (4th series), [1969] (Box-folder 5-3-7-8)
  - Unidentified publication, n.d. (Box-folder 7-9-8-5)
  - Fragments, n.d., [2 folders] (Box-folder 8-6)
- Series IV. Galley Proofs, 1966-[1969]
  - Masterplots Annual, 1966, [2 folders] (Box-folder 8-7)
  - Masterplots (4th series), [1969], [3 folders] (Box-folder 8-8)
- Series V. Authors, 1889-1967
  - A-B (Box-folder 9-1)
    - Barth, John, 1966-1967
    - Barthelme, Donald, 1964
    - Berry, Wendell, 1964
    - Bowles, Jane, 1966
  - C-E (Box-folder 9-2)
    - Carter, John Stewart, 1965
    - Cather, Willa, 1948-1967
    - Chappell, Fred, 1965
    - Connell, Evan S. Jr., 1963
    - Cowley, Malcolm, 1966
    - Crane, Stephen, 1930
    - Cummings, E. E., 1963
    - Dickey, James, 1962, n.d.
    - Edmonds, Walter D., n.d.
    - Eliot, T. S., 1963, n.d.
  - F (Box-folder 9-3)
    - Faulkner, William, [1962]
    - Francis, Robert, n.d.
    - Friedman, Bruce Jay, 1966
    - Frost, Robert, 1932-1962, n.d.
  - G-R (Box-folder 9-4)
    - Garrigue, Jean, n.d.
    - Guthrie, A. B. Jr., n.d.
    - Hall, Donald, 1955-1964
    - Hawkes, John, 1967
    - Hawthorne, Nathaniel, n.d.
    - Hemingway, Ernest, 1964
    - Holmes, Oliver Wendell, 1889
    - Kinsey, Ralph L., n.d.
    - Kohler, Dayton with James Still, [1961?]
    - Lehan, Richard, 1966
    - Lowell, Robert, 1965
    - MacLeish, Archibald, n.d.
    - Mayhall, Jane, n.d.
    - Nast, Thomas, n.d.
    - Oates, Joyce Carol, 1964-1966
    - Porter, Katherine Anne, 1965, n.d.
    - Price, Reynolds, 1963
    - Purdy, James, 1967, n.d.
    - Richter, Conrad, 1962-1966, n.d.
    - Roberts, Elizabeth Madox, n.d.
  - Sa-Ss (Box-folder 9-5)
    - Salisbury, Ralph J., n.d.
    - Sandburg, Carl, [1949-1953], n.d.
    - Singmaster, Elsie, [1939]
  - St, [2 folders] (Box-folder 9-6)
    - Stuart, Jesse, 1953-1968, n.d.
  - T-Z (Box-folder 9-7)
    - Taylor, Eleanor Ross, n.d.
    - Thompson, Lawrence S., 1967
    - Updike, John, 1959-1966
    - Van Doren, Mark, n.d.
    - Welty, Eudora, n.d.
    - Williams, William Carlos, n.d.
    - Wilson, James Southall, 1959
    - Wolfe, Thomas, 1941-1956
    - Yoder, Joseph W., n.d.
- Series VI. Books and Publishing, 1955-1971
  - Books and Reading by Dayton Kohler (New York: Salem Press), 1955 (Box-folder 9-8)
  - Literary Landmarks of Princeton (Princeton, NJ: Princeton University Library), 1968 (Box-folder 9-9)
  - The Hollins Critic, 1965-1971 (Box-folder 9-10)
  - Masterplots book lists, n.d. (Box-folder 9-11)